Hello and welcome back to our image and video processing class.
大家好 欢迎回到我们的图像与视频处理课程上来
This is our second week of class and we are going to talk about image and video
这是课程的第二周 我们将要讨论图像和视频的压缩
in compression which is probably one of the most successful areas of image and
这或许是图像和视频处理中最成功的领域之一了
video processing compression is used, all around and is actually an enabling
压缩技术是一种使能技术 它的应用非常广泛
technology as we are going to see. If you have some background in
正如我们将要见到的那样 如果你有一些
information theory or previous background in signal processing, some of the topics
信息论或者信号处理的基础知识
in this unit will be easier for you. But if you don't have background in those
这一单元中的一些话题对你而言会很简单 但是如果你没有相应的基础
areas, don't worry because the unit is going to be self contained and I'm going
也不必担心 因为这一单元相对独立 我也会
to teach you about the concepts that you need from those areas of information and
教你所需要的这些领域的相关概念
theory and signal processing so we can basically understand how image
包括信息论和信号处理 这样我们就可以理解
compression, JPEG, MPEG and our technologies work.
图像压缩 静态图像压缩(JPEG) 动态图像压缩(MPEG) 等技术是如何工作的
So let's start by illustrating why do we need image compression. This is not too
作为开始 让我们看看为什么我们需要图像压缩
hard to explain so let us do some numbers.
这解释起来并不困难 让我们算几个数字
Let just think that we have a image that has a 1000 x 1000 pixels.
假设我们有一张分辨率为1000 x 1000的图片
We know these actually, in today's standards, is actually what we call a low
我们知道 以现在的标准 这是一张
resolution image. But let's just use it for the sake of
低分辨率的图像 但是我们就用它吧
some numbering. And let's just assume that we need 8 bits
计算上方便些 假设我们需要8比特
as is normally standard. 8 bits to represent each one of the
正如一般标准规定的那样 用8比特来表示每一种颜色
colors, which means that we need 20 bits per
也就意味着我们每个像素需要24个比特
pixel. So we have an array, which is 1000 x 1000
所以我们得到了一个数组 大小为1000 x 1000
and 20 bits to represent the three colors.
再乘以用来表示三种颜色的24比特
So this is one image. And if we are doing video, it's just one
这是针对一张图像的计算 如果我们是计算视频的话
frame. We actually need 30 of these to get one
这只是一帧而已 我们实际上需要30张这样的图像来得到
second of video. We get 60 of these to get one minute of
一秒钟的视频 然后我们把60个这样的视频加起来得到一分钟的视频
video and then we have to multiply by 120 to get basically about two hours of our
然后我们再将它乘以120得到一部两个小时的
regular movie. So, what's these?
电影 所以这个式子的结果是多少？
These, the result of this is a very large number, very, very large number.
结果是一个非常大的数字 非常非常大
And you can do offline the computation, but you're going to basically agree.
你可以自己算一下 但是你会同意这个结论的
It's a very large number even for a relatively low resolution image.
一张低分辨率的图像就会产生很大的结果
So if we only have one image, we still have a very large number here.
所以哪怕我们只有一张照片 我们仍然有一个很大的结果
And we won't be able to basically save a lot of these images in our cell phones or
如果没有压缩的话 我们不可能把一大堆这样的照片
in our computers if we don't do compression.
存入我们的手机或者电脑中
So, the moment we start talking about images and video, we immediately get
所以当我们开始讨论图像和视频的时候 我们马上
very, very large numbers. And that's why we need image compression.
就遇到了很大很大的数字 这就是我们需要图像压缩的原因
We need to make possible to save those images, to save those videos, without
我们需要储存这些图像和视频
occupying so many bits in our computer or in our cell phone.
而不必在我们的手机或电脑中占据大量的空间
So that's a reason we need, basically, image and video compression.
这就是我们需要图像和视频压缩的一个原因
The question is, why can we do image and video compression?
问题是 为什么我们可以压缩图像和视频？
And there are many reasons. And we are going to talk about many of
这有许多原因 我们将会讨论它们
them. So one of the reasons is what normally is
其中一个原因通常被称为冗余
called redundancy and that's one of the first things that we are going to see.
这是我们首要的关注点之一
They are not every pixel value is equal, some pixel values appear more, some pixel
不是每个像素值都是相等的 有的像素值出现的多些 有的则
values appear less. As we can see in this image there is a
出现的少些 正如我们在这张图中见到的
lot of great values represent in this star, and only a few representing these
许多像素值被用来表示这个星星 一小部分用来表示
white lines and may be none representing certain colors.
这些白线 而表示某些特定颜色的像素值几乎没有
So we actually see that there is one, two, three, four colors here.
所以我们可以看到这张图里有一、二、三、四 四种颜色
So if this is represented with 8 bits, it comes up ways to use 8 bits, 256
如果用8比特来表示 也就是用256种可能性来表示4种颜色
possibilities to just represent 4. So we're going to exploit that.
这是一种浪费 所以我们将要利用这一点
There is another reason that we can do compression and there is on this a lot of
还有一个原因使得我们可以进行压缩 还是关于大量的冗余
redundancy. And this is illustrated in this image.
这点在这张图上表现的很直观
So let's assume that one of these lines has the constant grey value.
让我们假设其中一条线的灰度值为常数
Let's just say 128 for the sake of the example.
举个例子 就等于128好了
And let's imagine that this line is very, very long.
想象一下这条线非常的长
Let's assume, 10,000 pixels. So, they're are two ways at least, two
比如说10000个像素那么长 所以至少有两种
extreme ways to basically represent this. One is to 10,000 times say a 128.
极端的方法来表示这条线 一种是把128重复10000次
That will take us 10,000 bytes or 10,000 times 8 bits.
这会花掉10000字节也就是10000乘以8比特
So, we're going to say 128, 128, 128, 128 for 10,000 times.
我们要128 128 128 128 这样重复10000次
That looks like a lot of waste. On the other hand, if I say, starting
看起来非常浪费 或者换一种办法 我从这开始
here I say, 10,000 times 128. So I just give a number that says how
有10000个128 也就是说我给出了一个数字 用来说明
many times I'm going to repeat 128. That's much smaller amount of memory to
我要重复128次 这样用来存储的记忆空间就会小得多了
save that. I need to save the 128, which is the
我只要存储像素值128
pixel value, and I need to save the 10,000, the number of times that, that
以及其出现的次数10000
128 appears. And that's certainly much less to saving
相比保存128这个值10000次
those two numbers than 10,000 times saving 128.
只保存这两个数字无疑节省了非常多的空间
So this an extreme case, but a very important, and this happens often in
这是一个极端的例子 但是非常重要
images that we have uniform regions and basically some geometric coherence in the
它在有均匀区域或者几何一致性的图像中经常出现
image that we can exploit it to do compression.
我们可以利用这一点来进行压缩
So that's the second reason we can do compression and that also happens, by the
这就是我们能进行压缩的第二个原因 顺便说一句
way, in video as we're going to see. The third reason we can do compression is
这对视频压缩一样适用 我们能进行压缩的第三个原因就在这儿
right here. This is a flat image constant value.
这是一张纯色图像 灰度值为常数
So basically, there is a lot of irrelevant information in images.
这张图里有非常多的无关信息
There's a lot of information that we actually don't care to save, or we don't
这里有大量的我们并不关心的信息会被存储
care to save in a slightly different fashion.
或者说我们并不介意这些信息被存储时会有些许的不同
For example, if this is 128, maybe I don't care if I tell you it's 127.
比如说 如果这个值是128 我并不介意它被说成是127
Okay? And or maybe I don't care of it at all.
有可能我对这个值一点都不关心
So I might not care about the exact value, I might not care too much about
我可能不关心它的精确值是多少 可能不太关心
the information at all. So there is a lot of unnecessary
这些信息 所以这里有大量的无用信息
information, information which is irrelevant.
无关信息
So this are the three reasons that we can compress.
以上就是我们能进行压缩的三个原因
And we're going to exploit all these reasons.
我们将利用所有这些原因
And then we're going to get very large amounts of compression.
然后我们就能实现很大程度的压缩
There is a lot of compression as they say in the literature and part of the success
教材上有许多压缩的方法 其中一部分
of image compression is that it became standard.
成功的图像压缩方法最终成为了标准
And that's very important because if I save an image in my digital camera, I
这非常重要 因为当我在我的数码相机中保存了一张图像时
want every computer to be able to read it.
我希望所有的电脑都能读取它
I want to e-mail it to my friends and collegues and I want them to be able to
我想通过电子邮件把这张图片分享给我的朋友和同事 希望他们能够读取它
read it. So the way I save my image has to be
所以我存储照片的方式必须
compatible with the way that others read it.
与其他人读取它的方式兼容
And that's why there are so many, basically compression standards.
这就是有如此多的压缩标准的原因
In still images, these are three of the most popular, of course you know a lot
对于静态图像 这是最普遍的三种标准 当然 你应该对JPEG
about JPEG. JPEG is what they say most should have
有所了解 JPEG被大多数相机所采用
commerce use, and its going to be. basically, the way that we are going to
而且我们将会在接下来的视频里
teach a lot of the image processing, image compression, in the next hour or
讨论很多与图像处理和图像压缩有关的知识
so. There is a JPEG-LS a less which that's
这有一个标准称为JPEG-LS
what's called a loss less compression so exactly what you see is what you compress
是一种无损压缩 所以你所见的都会被压缩
so in that case there is no irrelevant information everything will be
在这种情况下 没有不相关的信息 所有的信息都会被压缩
compressed. And there is the new standard JPEG-2000
这儿还有个新标准JPEG-2000
so we're going to talk a lot about JPEG and JPEG-LS.
我们将重点讨论JPEG和JPEG-LS
In video, there is also standards. So once again, when I take a video, save
对于视频而言也有相应的标准 再说一次 当我拍摄了一段视频
it to my phone and send it to my friends, I want them to be able to read it.
保存到我手机里然后发送给朋友 我希望他们能够读取它
For that, they need to know how I did my compression.
为了能读取 他们需要知道我是如何进行压缩的
And of course, the most common ones are the MPEG family.
当然了 最常见的压缩标准就是MPEG家族
Although, there are other techniques, as listed here.
虽然这里还列出了其它的压缩技术
So. It's kind of a two sized trait.
这两个标准有些相辅相成的味道
Image and video compression has been so successful, that it made it to standards
它们在图像和视频压缩上是如此成功 以至于被制定成了标准
that everybody uses the same techniques. the fact that everybody uses the same
这使得所有人都在用着同样的技术 而所有人用着
techniques also made it very, very successful and very popular.
同样的技术这件事反过来也使得它非常的成功和普及
Now, digital camera manufacturers can confidently, with confidence, basically
如今数码相机制造商可以充满信心地
use JPEG because they know that everybody will be able to read it.
使用JPEG 因为他们知道所有人都能够读取这种格式
And that's why they are comfortable using it.
这就是为什么他们能如此安心地使用JPEG
General image impression techniques, that exploit all the types of issues, that I
一般的图像压缩技术都会利用到
mentioned a couple of slides, slides ago, work as follows.
我在前几页幻灯片中提及的图像的各种性质 它们的原理是这样的
There is, so you start from the image. Under is a mapper, so we take this array
从一张图像开始 经过一个映射器 (mapper) 也就是我们
that we talked in the previous week, of let's say 1,000 by a 1,000 points and we
把上周讲到的数组 比如说它有1000乘1000个点
transform it in a way that is more friendly to compression.
进行了变换使得其更容易被压缩
And we're going to talk about these maps. Some of these maps are going to be
我们来讨论下这些映射变换 有些映射变换
related to fully transforms, and is actually a cosine transform.
与傅里叶变换相关 实际上也就是是一个余弦变换
Some of these maps are going to be actually in the spatial domain, just
一些映射变换是发生在空间域上
looking at neighbor, neighboring pixels. We're going to talk about that.
依据相邻的像素进行变换 我们将会对此进行讨论
Then after that mapping, which basically brings the image into a space friendly to
在映射变换之后 图像在空间上变得易于压缩
compression, there is quantization.
然后下一步就是量化
We have already talked about quantization.
我们已经说过了量化
Quantization is the main step that introduces error.
量化是引入错误的主要原因
That introduces something that helps the compression, but limits me from being
它引进了一些易于压缩的东西 但是也限制了
able to reconstruct exactly the image. So, for example, we might have a pixel
对图像的精确重构 比如说 可能有一个像素
value, as we saw last time about 17. And my quantication technique might say
它的值为17 而量化技术或许会
that I need to divide by 2. And basically round it to the closest
将这个值除以2 然后再取整
integer from below and then multiply by two, something that we talked last time.
得到最接近的不大于该值的整数之后再乘2 这是我们上回讲到的
So I will end that with reconstructing, instead of 17, I will reconstruct 16.
所以我们这里会以重构结束 我们重构得到的值为16而不是17
So I introduce error by doing quantization.
所以量化会引入误差
And we're going to describe some of the best rechniques to do quantization, and
我们将描述一些最好的量化技术
actually also the quantization that is used in JPEG which is basically of the
实际上JPEG所用的量化技术就是我写在这的这种
type I just wrote here. The last part is the symbol in color.
最后一个步骤是利用符号编码器编码
Okay. I have done my, I have done my mapping, I
现在我已经完成了映射变换
have done my quantization. Now I have a value in my hand that I need
也完成了量化 现在我们已经有了一些数值  我需要的是把它们
to transmit. And I want the receiver on the other side
传输出去 我希望另一边的接收器
to get exactly that number. That's where information theory comes
能够得到准确的值 这儿信息论
into play because information theory tells us how to do this very, very
就起到了作用 因为信息论告诉我们如何使这一切
efficiently, both in computational time and to achieve compression.
在计算时间和压缩效率上都变得更有效率
This is the one that's going to basically exploit the redundancy that there is in
从使用更频繁的某些像素值的角度出发 信息论能够
the image from the point of view of using some pixel values more than others.
利用存在于图像中的冗余
And we're actually going to start from this.
我们将从这一点开始
That basically says, now I have done everything I need to do to my image.
现在我需要对图像做的处理都已经完成了
I want you to store or to transmit that pixel.
我希望你存储或者传输这些像素
Then, once you have compressed the image, you basically have a file with a
然后一旦你压缩了图像 你就得到了一个压缩过的文件
compression that's the encoder. The one that takes the image and
这就是编码器 它获取图像然后
compresses it. The decoder will basically decode the
压缩它 而解码器会将其解码
symbol. It won't do, basically, a quantization,
解码器并不会进行量化
because the quantization is done and then colored.
因为量化和编码都已经做过了
It might reverse it, for example, multiplying back by two.
解码器可能只是进行逆运算 比如说 重新乘上2
And then it will do the inverse of the map, and it will give you an image that
然后进行逆映射变换 就可以得到图像
might be the exact image if this is a lossless compression with no error, or it
如果是没有误差的无损压缩的话 那么图像是完好无损的
might be an approximation of the image, very often an approximation that we
或者说只是一个原图的近似品 一般而言这个近似品
cannot, with our naked eyes, actually realize the difference.
我们裸眼无法分辨出与原图的不同之处
So it would be a great approximation, like in JPEG or MPEG.
那样的话这就是一个好的近似 像JPEG和MEPG一样
So, that's basically the whole steps. And this also explains why we need
这就是全部的步骤了 这也解释了为什么我们需要标准
standards. If I use certain mapper the decoder needs
如果我用了某种映射变换 解码器需要
to understand the mapper so he can, he or she can invert it and I need to explain
知道这个映射变换 然后才能进行逆运算 我还需要告诉
to the decoder the symbols coding that are used so the decoder can do the
解码器我所用的符号编码方法 这样解码器才能
reverse of that symbol code. JPEG is an example of this.
逆运算得到符号编码 JPEG就是这样一个例子
And as I say, we're going to basically explain how JPEG works.
正如我所说 我们将介绍JPEG的工作原理
JPEG takes an image, and divides it in sub images.
JPEG首先得到一张图片 然后把它分割成小图片
I mean, it would take a whole image, and will divide it in blocks.
也就是说 它把一张完整的图像分割成一块一块
In particular, these blocks are going to be 8 by 8 pixels and we're going to see
这种块是8乘8像素的 我们将会知道为什么这样
why is that. Then that's a transform.
然后就是进行变换
This is the mapping we just took. In this case just going to be a discrete,
这就是我们刚说过的映射变换 在这儿 这个变换是
close entrance form, and we're going to explicitly talk about it, write down the
离散余弦变换 (Discrete Cosine Transform) 我们会详细地讨论它
formula's, and explain why this is a transform that is used.
给出相关的公式 并解释为什么使用它
It's going to do quantization of the type I just mentioned.
JPEG采用的量化方式也是我刚才提到的那种
Basically a JPEG is going to divide by a number and, and basically round it.
JPEG会将值除以某个数然后取整
Okay? it's going to divide by different numbers there's going to be some
不同的除数会产生不同的版本
adaptation that we are going to explain. And then, once it has done that, it's
我们也将对此作出解释 完成这些之后
going to do a symbol in color which is half man code which we're going to
就要进行符号编码 也就是霍夫曼编码 我们会解释它的
explain this way. But this is all what is done in JPEG.
这就是JPEG的全部流程
And you're going to see one of the optional homeworks I give you for the end
在这个单元结束后 我会给你一个可选的作业
of this unit is actually to implement JPEG in your computer.
就是在你自己的电脑上实现JPEG
It's not very hard as you're going to see.
你会发现这并不那么困难
And that's part of the reason this algorithm is so successful.
这种算法的成功一部分也得益于此
The decoder is going to decode this. It's going to do the inverse transform of
解码器会对其进行解码 运用离散余弦变换的逆变换
the DCT. It's going to put the blocks one next to
它把这些块一个挨着一个摆放
each other, and it's going to show you the image.
然后显示图像
Okay? And we're going to talk, this is down for
到这儿我们只完成了一种颜色的处理
one color. We're also going to also talk how the
我们还将讨论
different colors, the RGB are basically exploited.
不同颜色 例如是如何处理RGB的
Also by basically using some redundancy between the colors, we can actually get
通过利用不同颜色间的冗余 我们实际上
even more compression. So, JPEG is basically example of the
可以进一步地压缩 JPEG只是
prototype of the techniques of image compression with the mapping,
这种压缩技术原型的一个实例
that is this part, a quantization and a symbol encoder.
这个原型包括映射变换这个部分 量化 以及符号编码器
So and a very successful example of this technique.
所以JPEG是这种技术一个非常成功的实例
So I think it's time now to basically go and talk about each one of these blocks
我想是时候前进了 让我们来讨论这每一个步骤吧
in the text.
谢谢 // 教育无边界字幕组 | 风过成伤 | luoyetx | zeadoit 谢谢 // 果壳教育无边界字幕组 | 风过成伤 | luoyetx | zeadoit